Good morning. Yes, take a seat.
Welcome to the select committee this morning.
We resume submissions on the Conservation Amendment Bill, and
welcome our first submitter to the select committee, Milford
Sound Tourism Limited. So you've got 15 minutes with us this
morning, so we'll hand it over to you to open your remarks, and then we'll
open up for questions.
Thank you.
Tena koutou katoa, chair and members of the committee.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak here today.
My name's Hayley Preston, NSC of Milford Sound Tourism.
I'm speaking on behalf of them, or MSTL.
By way of background, MSTL is responsible for managing essential infrastructure
in Piopiotahi Milford Sound, and at Tahua Quay,
Knobs Flat, which is located along the Milford corridor.
We own and operate the harbor, wharves, visitor terminal, power and coach
parking, wastewater plants, and rubbish and recycling systems.
We're one of the largest concession fee payers in New Zealand.
Over many decades, MSTL has invested substantially in the infrastructure and the
visitor services that enables visitors to access Piopiotahi.
MSTL strongly supports the direction of the bill.
Many of the changes represent long overdue improvements to the regulatory system,
which we have struggled in recently.
However, there are several areas where we believe refinements are needed to ensure
the bill achieves its objectives in practice.
In particular, the legislative framework should provide sufficient
certainty to encourage long-term investment
and innovation while maintaining strong environmental safeguards.
MSTL supports a system that actively honors the Treaty of Waitangi
principles, the Crown's obligations that flow from this, and the Treaty settlement
obligations.
Drawing on MSTL's experience of operating for over 30 years within the conservation
estate, I would like to focus on several provisions of the
bill that we consider particularly important.
The first is maintaining conservation as the primary purpose of the Act.
MSTL supports responsible tourism and investment within the conservation estate,
but only where it supports conservation outcomes and does not compromise areas of
significant conservation value.
We're conscious that the proposed new provisions broaden DOC's role in enabling
development and economic opportunities.
There needs to be a clearer guidance to ensure conservation remains the dominant
consideration in decision making.
Secondly, we wish to address investment certainty within the
concession framework.
Across the country, there are certain concession activities that involve
substantial private investment.
Infrastructure investment in Piopiotahi Milford Sound is
unlike investment in many other locations.
We operate in a remote and risky environment, subject to extreme weather
conditions, natural hazard risk, along with high maintenance costs and
significant capital requirements.
The infrastructure we manage is designed and maintained over
extended time frames. Decisions made today often
involve significant investments that must deliver, remain fit for purpose, and
support operational needs for decades to come.
While the bill,
as written, recognizes that some concession holders are required to make
significant private investment and should be protected from the allocation process,
it does not offer certainty about how this criteria will be
met.
How concession holders will be treated at expiry requires clarification,
as well as to the extent which concession conditions can be amended during a
concession term, and the criteria that will apply to the future allocation
processes.
Providing greater certainty on these matters will encourage long-term investment
and support innovation within the conservation estate.
Thirdly, I would like to highlight MSTL's strong support of a visitor amenity
area, and especially one for Piopiotahi Milford Sound.
Any concerns raised by Papatipu Rūnanga in relation to the visitor
amenities area should be worked through via engagement with Māorienua.
Piopiotahi is one of New Zealand's most iconic destinations, and remains
one of our most natural visitor attractions.
Over the next 12 months, we expect to
have over 950,000 people arrive. Accommodating that
volume of visitors in a safe and efficient, and environmentally
responsible manner requires significant infrastructure and careful long-term
planning. It is not simply about providing tourism services.
It is about ensuring that visitors can access and enjoy this remarkable place while
protecting the natural, cultural, and heritage values that make it so special.
Over the coming decade, Piopiotahi will require millions and millions of dollars of
investment into critical infrastructure.
This includes visitor facilities, transport and parking solutions, harbor and
marine infrastructure, and utilities,
along with other supporting services that are necessary to manage visitors
appropriately and maintain a high-quality visitor
experience. These investments require long planning
horizons and confidence that the future development will align with the long-term
vision for the area.
We see visitor amenity areas as a way to provide an important framework to
support that outcome. Rather than considering infrastructure and visitor
services on a piecemeal basis, a visitors amenity area would enable
strategic, coordinated, and a place-based approach to planning.
It would provide greater certainty for investors,
operators, mana whenua, and local communities, and the Department of
Conservation about where infrastructure should be located, how visitor pressures
can be managed, and how conservation outcomes can be achieved alongside
visitor access.
Importantly, we believe this approach could help concentrate development in
appropriate locations, therefore reducing pressure on more sensitive areas,
while ensuring that essential visitor infrastructure is planned and delivered in an
integrated way. For a destination such as Te Ahikato Rohe when the
balance between visitor access and conservation protection is critical, we
consider the visitor amenities area to be a positive and practical tool
that will support both the visitor experience and long-term stewardship of this
extraordinary place.
Lastly, the final point I would like to touch on is the international visitor
access charges. MSTL supports the concept of international
visitor access charges, where they are efficient, proportionate, and clearly
linked to the conservation outcomes.
Destinations such as Te Ahikato Rohe Milford Sound attract visitors from around the
world who come to experience New Zealand's most iconic natural
landscapes. The infrastructure required to manage those visitors while
protecting the environment, maintaining visitor facilities, and supporting
conservation outcomes comes at a significant cost.
It is therefore reasonable to consider mechanisms that allow international visitors
to make a direct contribution towards the protection and management of the places
they enjoy.
However, we believe any access charging system must be simple to administer,
transparent in its purpose, and designed to minimize compliance costs for both
visitors and operators. The funds collected should be retained within
or clearly allocated to the locations they are generated, so that visitors can see
the direct connection between their contribution and the improved
conservation infrastructure and visitor management outcomes.
In closing, MSTL supports the bill's objectives of modernizing the
conservation management.
We ask that the committee considers our proposed refinements, all of which
were included in our submission, which we believe will support stronger
conservation outcomes. Thank you for your time today, and I welcome any questions
from the committee.
Thank you very much. Look, we will go first-- We've got a lot of questions,
actually. We'll go first to Priyanka.
I was hoping I'd get two, Madam Chair, but anyway,
I'll
go with one. You've mentioned through your written submission and
oral the need for certainty for investments and for large
operators like yourself.
Mm-hmm.
One of the main shifts in this proposed legislation is the concentration of
decision-making power with the minister.
Mm-hmm.
In quite a top-down approach. It takes out local decision-making, which
was quite a consideration when the act was first designed or
drafted.
How does that work with your need for certainty
across successive governments?
It's almost as if we don't know where the rules are going to land at the moment
within the bill itself. So we don't know the
criteria around allocation. We don't know what's going to happen at the end of term
and
unless that's written in and somehow advised, we don't know how the
minister or whichever decision maker it's going to be, is
going to be able to apply those rules to people who are trying to invest today.
Yeah.
So you would want a bit more certainty in the primary legislation rather
than just the NCPS. Is that-
Yes. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
Celia.
Thank you. Thank you for coming in.
Thank you for
doing your very best to make conservation and tourism work together.
I was interested in your comments about the visitor amenities
areas.
Mm-hmm.
And to what extent those could be more
usefully defined sometimes at, for example, outside national parks
rather than within them. I know there's been a long history of thinking about
having
more of the visitor amenities area at Te Anau and then
getting people to Piopiotahi,
not two people, one car, and creating all those problems.
Having last time I went there, I cycled in on the
Sound2Sound.
Nice.
I don't think I was too much of a problem for the infrastructure.
But
there have been those discussions in the past.
Does this part of the act help or hinder that kind of
planning?
I think in specific locations where they could be located outside the national
park, that's a fair assumption. Milford Sound is an hour
45 from the closest small town as
well. So it makes sense to have a visitor amenities
area at the end of the road there, and potentially other locations along
the road where you're going to have hubs of infrastructure.
It needs to be able to be easily planned
at those different hubs, and it's
just the distance from the main town is too far.
Thank you. Grant.
Yeah, just I'm really interested in the investment certainty
angle. So your concessions at the moment are for how long as a rule?
How long do you-
30 years.
Yeah.
Okay, and obviously, when it comes up for renewal, and you've got to go through a
process, and all the investment required and so forth, how do you
balance Having a competitive process, because other people
probably would love, I suspect, to come and run a business in the same place
that you are, because it's such a unique place.
How do you balance that with the certainty that you're looking for?
And
also tied into that,
if someone else won the concession, then you've got
to get the value out yourselves-
Mm-hmm
... as the current investors. How do you see all that mix working?
You need to understand at the beginning, when you enter into the concession, what
the end game's going to be.
Yeah.
That is
a crucial-
Yeah
... part of it-
... as well. And then you make your investment decisions based on
what your end period is.
Mm-hmm.
So for long-term infrastructure, you would be looking for
60 years-
Yeah
... for some of that, and then you factor that into your planning
around what that end is. And
it's critical to get market value-
Yeah
... at that point-
... at the end, from any party, even if it's taken
over by the Crown, by DOC at that point, if they want to manage that
infrastructure.
Or another, if it was a competitive process for a concession-
Yeah
... if someone else came in and won the-
Yes
... got the concession, then you'd expect they'd pay market value for the
assets that you'd developed.
There's significant investment that goes into-
Oh, 100%
... the infrastructure, and even in the operation side of things as well.
Yeah.
And branding and all
of the intellectual property that comes along with-
Yeah
... not just only the infrastructure as well.
So okay, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Ryan.
Thanks, Chair. Thanks, Hayley, for your submission.
In point 40 of your conclusion, you
recommend that we adopt amendments that honors the Crown's obligations on the
Treaty of Waitangi, reserve meaningful treaty partner,
stakeholder participation, et cetera.
And then in point 16,
you reference that it looks like
you defer the response of
this to Te Runanga o Ngāi Tahu as the tribal representative body-
Mm-hmm
... as to how the bill should give effect to the principles of the Treaty, but you
don't explicitly explain anything in your submission.
Is there anything that you see that's concerning, or where do you see a
potential
weakening or the-
I believe for all concession holders, it's important to give more
clarity around section four.
And as Ngāi Tahu is now a shareholder of MSTL-
Yeah
... I'm deferring all of that to mana whenua.
Yeah, okay, but nothing explicit that you saw as the entity?
Only more around the clarity.
Okay, thanks.
Okay, time for one last question from-
Yeah.
Thank you so much for your submissions.
I was a submission as well on the visitor amenity
areas.
Mm-hmm.
And you mentioned world-class visitor experiences, and a
concern that we've heard with the bill is the potential for essentially
big money, big tourism to be able to come in
and basically invest, but to the exclusion
of the public-
Mm-hmm
... everyday New Zealanders. Do you see
that being an issue at all or with Pio Pio
Tahi because of the space constraints in that?
Is public access generally just a bottom line,
or can you see risks where basically money might be
able to buy space or buy development for exclusion
of everyday Kiwis?
I think it will only enhance the experience everyday Kiwis will have.
It will provide more facilities in remote locations
for them to use and access, and I think it will only
enhance it.
Okay, so you don't see exclusion, or
only people who pay the big dollars would be able to access these areas?
No. There's a wide range of people that come in and visit Milford.
Not everyone goes on a cruise. They come and enjoy the local walks.
They will be improved, and all the other wonderful things in the area.
Cool. That's helpful. Thank you.
Thank you. I think that's a good spot to-
Thank you
... end that submission. Thank you for your submission.
It's really good to just learn about all the practicalities and what you're facing,
and yes, the beautiful Milford Sound.
Yes. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you all.
So we'll now move to our next submitter, Real NZ.
Yes.
Yeah.
Who are joining us in person today.
Good morning.
Welcome to the select committee this morning.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you for your
opening address, and then we'll open up for questions. So over to you.
Thank you very much for your time
today. My name's Dave Beach. I'm the Chief Executive of Real NZ.
With me, I've got Paul Norris, who's our Chief Conservation Officer.
Also worth noting that Paul sits on the New Zealand Conservation Authority,
but is here today speaking in his role as Chief Conservation Officer at a
35-year-old, a 35 year, not year old
employee of Real NZ.
Special job.
Yeah.
And we also have Erin Burka, our General Counsel.
So we'll highlight a few things and then welcome questions obviously.
But, as you would have seen in our submission, Real NZ's been going for 70 years.
We hold about 35 DOC concessions,
and we put through 1.4 million guests across our experiences.
Some of you may have been on the Eunsor in Queenstown, or one of the beautiful
cruises in Milford Sound, or on one of our ski fields, Cardrona or Treble Cone.
So, a big range of experiences. We have about 1,500 employees.
We're one of the largest tourism operators in the country.
But at our heart is our conservation purpose.
So our founders, Les and Olive Hutchins, when they founded the company in '54, had
a strong conservation ethos, and our purpose is to help the world fall in love with
conservation. And we do that through a whole range of not only our
experience delivery to our guests, but in also a lot of direct action
that we take through massive investment in planting and trapping and looking after
the environment that we operate in.
So foundational for our company and our belief, and if you speak to any of our
staff, they'll tell you that conservation is at the core of what we do, and we
recognize how important that is to the tourism economy So look, in
short, we strongly support the bill with some
refinements. We think it's a massive step in the right direction.
Broadly speaking, the principles that have underlined our submission
are that the system as it is now has been broken.
Some of our concessions have taken more than a decade to be
renewed.
That process is changing and is improving, but the
system improvements proposed in the bill are well overdue and needed.
We support sustained and managed growth in tourism.
One of our foundational beliefs is the more people that get to experience
our beautiful nature in a high-quality way, then the more inclined they'll be to
look after it and invest in it.
We think that DOC needs resources to do that,
and it's currently under-resourced at the moment, so strongly
support the raising of funds through access levies
and through more economic activity on the conservation
estate. And the more that the settings are put in place to support
partnership with private investment and other entities to support
that with conservation guardrails around it, then we think that's going to be
better off for the conservation estate.
So with that, I'll hand over to Paul.
Thanks, Dave. Thanks for the opportunity to talk at the select committee today.
So I'm firstly Paul Norris, Chief Conservation Officer with RealNZ.
So look, I'm going to read a few notes here, but firstly, conservation must stay as
a top priority for the Department of Conservation as its roles
expands. The new clause 6EA gives DOC a much
broader enabling role in economic development of conservation land.
This is materially broader than today's more
limited purpose
relating to fostering use for recreation and tourism, where not
inconsistent with their conservation.
We support DOC being empowered to enable investment
opportunities, carefully planned and appropriately managed
use of development in parts of the conservation estate
where it can enhance visitor experiences while supporting
the long-term protection of New Zealand's unique biodiversity.
However, because it could also apply to use of conservation land for
any purpose, not just the current settings of recreation or tourism,
this expanded function may result in competing priorities,
and so we recommend that guardrails are put in place to guide
prioritization and decision making.
RealNZ
suggests including three guardrails.
One, turning the Act's long title into a proper purpose clause,
being to promote the conservation of New Zealand's natural and
historic resources.
Two, prioritizing DOC's core conservation functions,
6A and C,
above the new economic opportunity function.
Three, replacing the text to the greatest extent
practicable under the Act and other enactments
in proposed clause 6A with, to the extent consistent
with the purpose of this Act, mirroring the existing feta in
6E.
We also would like the word tourism put back into DOC's
functions explicitly. The bill's explanatory notes tell us
that the concept is being incorporated into 6EA.
But we believe that tourism and conservation have a unique and
mutual beneficial relationship, and we believe tourism deserves its own
recognition. I'll just add a couple more words here.
Most international visitors visit the DOC estates
using concessionaires to get that high-quality experience.
And I think it's really important to make sure that that is maintained and enhanced
going forward and those opportunities are
developed further with concessionaires.
They simply provide a safe, guided, world-class experience on the
DOC estate. And for a big group of people that come to our country,
that's what they come into our country for a holiday for.
And so making sure that that is retained, I think, is extremely important.
We see the requirements for DOC to enable economic opportunities
through use and development of conservation land as positive, provided
that is appropriate use and the development that results in good
conservation outcomes.
An example of this is the RealNZ operations of the Te Anau
Glowworm Caves in the Fiordland National Park, where we hold a
concession to guide our guests through the caves.
To support this experience, we have built a wharf to get guests there,
walkways
to and within the caves, and a small building to provide
educational
interpretation as part of their experience.
These facilities help
offer a high-quality experience, and this kind of development
is conservation in action and should be the kind of
use and development that 6EA is meant to enable.
I'll just hand over to my colleague, Erin, now to
talk about her section. Thank you.
Thank you. Kia ora. So I would like to talk a little bit about concessions.
Concessions are vitally important to our business.
As Dave mentioned, we hold around 35 concessions on conservation land, and we
like to keep investing,
keep providing those high-quality visitor experiences for our guests.
There are a couple of things within the bill as it's currently drafted that we
think have the potential to undermine
investor appetite. So a couple of examples there are,
there's inability to impose standardized conditions on existing
concessions,
with no ability to vary them for complex cases.
And by that, I mean like most of our concessions, of those 35, they will have a
number of things in there. There may be a mooring, may be access to
facilities, there may be leases of parts of land,
transport across the lake, and that's all within the one concession
So the
ability to impose these standardized
conditions also comes with a proviso that there's no compensation
if your rights are removed or there's some kind of negative impact on
you.
In the context of a 25 year concession with millions of
investment, that has the ability to undermine the certainty around that, and
it's harder to make your business case stack.
Another major thing there for us is just around what happens at expiry.
So at the moment, it's not really clear whether when you get to the end of your
concession, will it be put out to an allocation process?
Will we get advanced notice of that? If so, how much?
And what will happen to the business that we may have spent 25 years building?
So, in our view, at least two years notice would be appropriate, and then that
could be scaled according to the length of the concession and
the investment that you put in.
We also firmly believe that expiry of the concession, concessionaires
should be able to decide whether to remove their assets, to sell the business
to the incoming operator, and that should be at a price that reflects not only
the physical assets that are on the site, but also the
25 years that they've spent building the goodwill, building the business, building
the reputation that attracts guests across to New Zealand.
If assets were simply transferred across to the Crown or transferred across to the
new operator at no value,
concessionaires just wouldn't be incentivized to continue doing those upgrades
and keep that
quality level really high.
So just probably one other point I'd just like to briefly touch on is, we really
support the move to the pre-approved and exempt concessions framework.
We think that'll do a great job in freeing up DOC resources to focus on some more
complex cases.
But as with other large tourism operators, we do have the requirements for a
long-term concession, and we have a number of different components in there.
So ours will always be complex cases that fit outside of that.
And that's
true for most large tourism operators as well.
And a concern for us is that we don't yet know how visitor numbers will be
managed. In some of those really popular spots, we want to make sure that
the numbers of people that are going in there are able to be
proactively managed to keep that quality experience high.
Also, just really quickly, I'd like to touch on the role of independent
oversight and keeping a public voice in the system.
So, as the question raised earlier with
MSTL's
piece there, a lot of the decision making has
been left in the minister's hands, and the role of the Conservation
Authority and conservation boards has been reduced back to an advice and
consultation role.
We think that possibly goes a little bit too far.
We think those bodies in particular bring really deep subject matter expertise,
and they also have a really good community perspective, which we think is really
valuable. As a minimum, we would say they should have a formal recommendation role,
but also support the approval role that they currently have.
And we also think the right to be heard on submissions is important, especially for
the National Conservation Policy Statement, area plans, et cetera.
Not just the right to make written comments, but actually to come and talk to
people as well, and we've found that in the past, that's actually elicited some
really great insights for us in terms of local concerns about
us operating on conservation land and how we might best deal with those.
I'll just hand back over to Dave.
Great. Thanks, Erin. Back to you, Chair.
Yeah, no, thank you. Really useful submission.
Some really good insights there. Look, we've got a few questions.
We'll go to Priyanka first.
Thank you.
I have a two-pronged question. The first part of it
is tourism being removed from the purpose
of the Act. You want it back. I'm keen to get an understanding of
what
the
risk is of not having it explicitly stated in there,
and I'm also keen to get your sense on what kind of development, given that
the shifts in this bill are to allow development on
conservation land outside of recreation tourism.
Keen to get your sense of what kinds of things you think might be captured in
that.
Yeah, thanks. On your first question, look, we fundamentally believe that tourism
and conservation have gone hand in hand for as long as the
conservation estates existed, and that
fundamentally, the more people that experience the conservation estate
through tourism,
the better off it will be and the more investment will be generated to go back into
the estate. So one of the things that we talk about with our access levies is that
a significant proportion of the access levies go back into the estate, and
we think that's going to be a key economic generator for helping solve some of the
resource constraints that are in place with the DOC estate at the
moment.
Second question around recognition of other
business enterprise on the DOC estate. Yeah, we're open-minded on that.
We're not going to speak on behalf of other
sectors, I guess, with that. But Erin, did you want to make any comments on
that one?
I think traditionally there have been comments that things like fair
keeping and those kind of activities haven't necessarily fit into the tourism and
recreation space. So I think where things are consistent with
conservation, tying it back, as Paul mentioned, to that purpose
and making sure that what we're doing is good for conservation is important for us.
Thank you. Grant?
Yeah. First of all, I must admit, I admire anyone that's been trying to run a
ski field. So again, good on you, and someone who's been to
Treble Cone numerous times. Amazing facility. Thank you.
But just my question is- The concessions, and you heard my
questions to the previous presenter, is that I can see that the
dilemma around that length of concession relative to
investment, what would be in an ideal-- How would you
in an ideal world like to see that? Because obviously we're talking significant
investments here, right?
Yeah. Firstly, we recognize that you don't want to create a system
which is not open to competition, right?
Yeah.
You can't have monopolies, right?
But what we're saying is that we are investing significant sums of money in the
complex arrangements like we have at Triple Cone.
Yeah.
Then that needs to be reflected in the end of term provisions.
So,
I won't go into the detail. We ended up with a really good outcome on that
concession, which we renewed recently.
But-
How long is that interest?
Thirty years. Yeah. So, essentially the more investment and the longer the
term concession, the longer you need to renew it.
Otherwise, if you've got a risk of your assets being handed over at book
level or zero-
Yeah
... then naturally in the last decade of that concession-
You wind down
... you'll wind down. And so you need to have a renewal process
that accounts for, I guess, the level of investment involved and the tenure of the
concession.
Would you look to start a renewal process quite early?
And if you've got a 30 year concession, say at 20 years?
100%.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah.
So then,
and with the concept of being, this is only going to take a year to work through.
Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah.
Not 10 years. Yeah.
Just time for one last question. Celia.
Oh, thank you very much. Yes, I was interested in--
and I think you're doing a great job, don't get me wrong.
But I was interested in point 29, your paragraph
29.
Yeah.
You make the point that the minister may issue a notice suspending the
pre-approved status of an activity if adverse effects were
observed, and I suppose that could be anything from boats don't come up too close
to dolphins to other, more physical
infrastructure problems.
And then you say having to cancel basically the trips that would
then be coming in. Isn't that just such a great
incentive to not
trip over these things with the adverse effects anyway?
I just wondered if you could expand a little bit about what
adverse effects you think shouldn't mean
that the next trip should be canceled.
Yeah.
I think our concern there was really more at a macro level.
So if it was being observed that there were too many people in a particular area,
and the minister decided to suspend activity there,
through no fault of ours, we may have to be-
Oh, so it could be other people's-
Yes.
So, like the-
I see.
Yes.
Now, I'm not sure whether I agree or not, but I certainly
understand.
Yeah. No, that might need to be dealt with
differently, wouldn't it? Mm.
Just very quickly, just because, you did touch on it earlier, the six
EA. And obviously you are broadly in support of that, but
you just want to have more recognition within there of tourism.
Correct.
Is that-
And the conservation guardrails.
And, yeah.
The conservation guardrails.
We think-
Yeah, so you just feel it needs to be reworded to capture that.
Yeah. We feel that, you might find this strange coming from a business operator,
but we think to the greatest extent practicable goes too far.
Mm-hmm.
And it just needs a few conservation guardrails around there.
Okay. Yeah
... so that we all work together to preserve the conservation estate.
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, thank you.
No, really helpful.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thanks very much for your submission today.
Appreciate it.
Might want to do the-
Any chance those ski costs going skiing, coming down?
Jeez, a billion hundred dollar bill's gone up there.
He's got the gold card anyway, so.
B****r off.
Well, if the concession levies come down, we'll look at it.
Very good.
So we now welcome our next submitter,
Federated Mountain Clubs of New Zealand Incorporated.
Welcome to the select committee this morning.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you to introduce
and then open up the questions.
Thanks, Madam Chair. You're from the Hawke's Bay, right?
Yes, that's right.
Good. The mighty Hawke's Bay.
Yes.
I'm a regional New Zealander, I don't think as many of you are.
I'm up from Otago, came up yesterday.
So, thanks for having us.
Yeah, look-
Your name, sorry, mate.
My name, sorry, mate, it's Alan Brent.
Alan.
Alan Brent.
I'll just start with a bit of an introduction because, in New Zealand I think the
mihi mihi is customary. So I'm
Pākehā, right, but I can trace my roots back to 1200
in Somerset in England. A guy by the name of Severinus de Turre.
He was a Norman.
He was the Abbot of Gladstone Abbey Cathedral.
Since then, we've been ship builders, clergy, and
latterly, lawyers. So that's a bit about me.
And I'm here-
Things were going well until the last bit.
Yeah, I know, right? Yeah, sorry about that.
Lawyers, right? And
look,
my climbing roots, I'm here for Federated Mountain
Clubs and I'm the president of Federated Mountain Clubs.
And
my background is in climbing, right.
Climb and paragliding. So, I've walked the length of the South
Island from Cape Farewell through to Foveaux Strait, through the
Alps. I've climbed a number of highest peaks.
We've got unclimbed peaks in New Zealand.
Managed to get up a few of those, sort of first ascents and stuff like that.
Wow.
So really
great. And
I'm here for Federated Mountain Clubs, which is what it sounds like.
It's a federation of mountain clubs.
We were founded in
1931 and
we have 23,000 New Zealanders are members, right.
So
possibly doing pretty well next to some of the political parties,
with all due respect. And we know
that there are around about 100,000 people in our
orbit, and
Our membership's ticking up.
We obviously like to think it's because of things we're doing, but we think it's
actually probably because of things like concerns around this bill.
Okay.
A reason to talk about roots is really
just to say that what we're talking about when we're talking
about amending conservation legislation is we're talking
about our special places, we're talking about
home. Okay.
So, this is why you've
seen the depth of feeling in recent weeks, and we're really
coming from that perspective of home.
The problems the bill are trying to solve are quite interesting.
They're in this document. I'll leave it for the clerk.
It's called Modernizing Conservation Land
Management, and it's from November
2024.
There are four things that
the bill says it's trying-- Well, the program
of reform is trying to solve.
They're set out in section three
of that document. And I'll just run through them.
One, and I'll let you know what we think about that.
One, the planning system is too complicated.
So we agree with this, right? It's a bit anachronistic in
places, and so we've set out what we think about that in our
submission.
But as you just heard from our friends at RealNZ,
it's kind of gone too far the other way.
It's kind of gone so simple that there's been a loss of nuance, and
we all know that our different regions around New Zealand are quite different,
right? Like Hawke's Bay is not like Otago.
Northland is not like Wellington, for example.
So, that sort of piece of regional nuance, we
think that the
proposed system will lose that nuance to a
degree that isn't healthy. So, that's one problem.
A second problem, concession decisions take too long.
Now, that's not really our bag, but,
and take the advice of our friends who just submitted, but,
I do note that the minister himself,
if you go to Beehive website, you can see on eighth July
last year, he put out a release saying that the problem was
largely sorted under the current law.
So it's kind of like, do we have a problem here?
We do. Well, we do. We do indeed, and as we set
out in our submission, there's plenty of room to improve the concessions
process. But we say that a lot of great work's been done already, so
this isn't really an issue we need to dwell on too much.
The third issue, the government getting better performance and
outcomes out of concessions. So this is about
perhaps the value that the government can extract from a
concession.
And it's been interesting hearing about the
competitive allocation comments just now and wanting some predictability
around that. We think that the
bill doesn't really offer that predictability.
Don't really know why that's been avoided.
It seems like there's obviously the Ngāi Tai ki Tāmaki case,
which said that allocation may imply a reasonable degree of preference for
iwi, and that might be a difficult issue.
But I think that's one area that does need work.
And the fourth is that the government has limited flexibility to
manage land.
And on this, we say, coming back to the roots, well, this is public conservation
land. This is
our land and conservation,
rooted in the word conservative.
To not do too much, not change too abruptly.
You actually don't want too much flexibility. Okay.
So, Meatloaf, he reckoned two out of three wasn't bad
when you're talking about things you love and hate.
Great song.
Yep. And,
possibly looking at one point five out of four.
I don't know if you're awarding half marks there, but, look, that's not to
diss
anyone. We just think started with the wrong questions.
The Conservation Act is the cultural and
political settlement for what we'll do with
our public conservation land.
So the place to start with that kind of a
settlement is, what's it for?
Who's it for?
And who decides?
Now, what's it for?
You've just heard from RealNZ that
they want people to fall in love with conservation land.
It's pretty hard to fall in love with something you don't respect.
So you have to put conservation up at number one.
Right. That's what we would say. What's it for?
Conservation guardrail, essential.
Who's it for? Well, it's in the name.
It's public conservation, and again, it's ours.
So you're talking about home,
and that sort of starts to come into public rights
of being heard, and so on. And who
decides these things? We agree,
with our friends at RealNZ, that
bringing things into Wellington,
too much is not going to be durable.
It's going to lead to an unhappy sort of end.
And a funny story about this one. I'll leave this with the
clerk,
as well. This is our 50-year book
We're now 96.
And this tells the story of when in
1979, 1980,
the Muldoon government made similar proposals
to bring all of the management into Wellington
from the authority and boards.
And your predecessors in this committee
considered that, and they walked away from that
proposal for the kinds of reasons that we've submitted and Relin
Z also gave you.
So that's just to say that if you go through with where this is
going-
Yeah
... you're doing something even Rob didn't manage, so well done.
So look, that's all I'll say.
If you have any questions, I'd be glad to
speak to them.
Thank you. Thank you very much for that submission.
We do have a couple of questions. Grant McCollum.
Yeah. Visitor amenity areas. You seem to have some concerns
according to your submission.
Yeah.
Okay. You say it's de facto
privatization. People are going to have to make these work, invest a lot of
money to make the visitor experience-
Sure
...
a lot better, right, for everybody, not just tourists.
Yeah.
So I'm just trying to... I'm struggling with what your concern is.
Even your own members, if they're on the way, the gateway to a
particular park, and they've got the ability to utilize those visitor amenity
areas. I'm just trying to understand what your concerns are.
Yeah. Well, it's interesting you mention a gate.
Okay.
Well, you said gateway, but a gate.
So we have freedom of access, for example-
Mm
... to conservation land.
Yeah.
And that's sort of regarded as a birth right.
Mm-hmm.
Okay. So
now, we don't want to get into too detail here today,
but these things look like they could support exclusive
possession, right, which would displace a right of access.
So that's one example of a concern.
Hold on. Sorry, you've got me completely confused.
What do you mean it can displace a right of access?
It's a big statement.
Well, we think that the drafting supports that.
But they're building in a visitor amenity area, not some wing that's going
to stop you going into a national park.
Well, the thing is, right, the drafting can support-
Mm
... say, a game park or something on conservation land.
Mm-hmm.
So like-
Sorry, say what? Say that again
... a game park.
Mm.
So you might
want to go hunting exclusively, and people do come to New Zealand for that.
Mm.
Now-
That's funny
... our hunting friends might not like that.
Something there on business.
Yeah. But-
A supplementary on that, Priyanka.
Yeah.
It is a new statutory term, visitor
amenity areas.
And it's not well defined in the legislation either.
So I was just wondering if you could give us an example.
I guess you said game parks-
Mm
... just now. But
getting to the
crux, I guess, of your anxiety, what do you envision could
happen as a result of the-
Sure
... drafting currently?
So
I've been involved for FMC in our engagement with the
Milford Opportunities Project, right-
Mm-hmm
... which would be the kind of thing that would go into a visitor amenity area.
Now, we totally support what
happened there. They had some great proposals. We're right behind them.
But what we said was, "Look,
you've got one road into Fiordland National Park,
the Clinton Road, and what you want to do is have something for
everyone." So if there is a physical gate that would
prevent New Zealanders, for example-
But no one's talking about that. That's not in the-
Can we...
Yeah, just let him
finish, please.
Yeah. Thanks.
Yeah.
Chair.
Yeah, appreciate that.
We think that obviously, you've got to do something on the
ground to manage demand, right? Because we want to
have a quality experience at Milford Sound.
The issue is
too many people there, right? So we've got to sort of modulate the demand.
Okay? So you've got to have a gate of some form.
Now, if that gate takes the form of something like a number plate recognition,
fine. But if it actually prevents people getting in there, not fine.
So that's the kind of concern. Does that help?
So it's too broad, basically.
Too broad.
Okay. Thanks. Thank you. Look, we'll have got time for one last question.
Lam.
Yeah. Thank you so much for your submission.
I wanted to pick up on
the guts of the conservation part, because you're pointing out, for
example, that even though the minister has made
comments around changing some of the provisions in the bill and the
causes, that nothing has actually changed, and that's
our role here at Select Committee.
Mm-hmm.
How do you think we could be able to work with groups
like yourself to actually make sure that we're not
going down as, in your words, this highly regrettable
road, and we're actually ensuring that this conservation
purpose is at the core? Is it just the normal select
committee process? What would FMC like to see?
Because I note that you wrote to the committee about this.
Yes, I did, and thanks for
that correspondence. Yeah, look, so
obviously when you've got a normal government bill,
the government's in behind its core tenets, right?
Okay, pretty normal.
It seems that there is disagreement about this 6EA
thing, right? And obviously there's been the
withdrawal of the land sale and exchange provisions.
Okay, so we've got a government bill where its core planks perhaps aren't
supported.
And so we think, again, we're talking about the cultural
and political settlement for public conservation land. It's a big deal, right?
Core to our national identity. So,
for me to come up from Otago and have 15 minutes to talk to you in a
sort of lovely room in Wellington, that's kind of not appropriate to those
kinds of issues. So we need a responsible public
discussion. And last thing I'd say on this is, I
think you're going to report after the election, if I'm
right on that. I really hope you'll encourage your colleagues in the 55th
Parliament to
put it out again when we've got a solid bill that we can all look
at where we know where we stand.
Mm-hmm.
Does that-
Yeah, no, that's really helpful.
Yeah.
Yeah. No, thank you for that. And thank you for your submission
today, and thanks for coming all the way up from Central Otago.
Appreciate it.
Yes, and you can be assured that obviously the Select Committee, our job is to
work through the legislation and make sure we do get it right into the future.
So we appreciate your feedback. Really good submissions. Thank you.
Thanks very much. Thanks a lot.
Thank you.
Good morning.
So that brings us to the end of our public session for this
morning